<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/revuedescolonies/revuedescolonies-data/main/odd/tei_revue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/revuedescolonies/revuedescolonies-data/main/odd/tei_revue.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- 
  THIS FILE IS GENERATED
  DO NOT EDIT
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="entities">
    <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="ADp">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Alexandre Dumas</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Born in 1802 to Marie-Louise Elisabeth Labouret and Thomas-Alexandre Dumas Davy de la Pailleterie, a Revolutionary War general from Saint-Domingue, Alexandre Dumas (also known as Alexandre Dumas père) was among the most popular French playwrights and novelists of the nineteenth century. Dumas received early education in his native Villers-Cotterets from Abbé Grégoire, who ran a local school. By the 1830’s, Dumas was a successful dramatist and a leading figure in the Romantic movement, though he was not favored by contemporary critics. Over the course of the twentieth century, Dumas’ canonical status would be solidified, culminating with the transfer of his remains to the Pantheon in 2002.</p>
                <bibl>Daut, Marlene L. “Haiti and the Black Romantics: Enlightenment and Color Prejudice after the Haitian Revolution in Alexandre Dumas’s Georges (1843).” <title>Studies in Romanticism</title>, vol. 56, no. 1 (2017): 73–92.</bibl>
                <bibl>Desormeaux, Daniel. “L’amour Nègre Chez Alexandre Dumas.” In <title>Dumas Amoureux : Formes et Imaginaires de l’Éros Dumasien</title>, edited by Julie Anselmini and Claude Schopp, 373–87. Presses universitaires de Caen, 2021.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martone, Eric, ed. <title>Alexandre Dumas as a French Symbol Since 1870</title>. Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2021.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Born in 1802 to Marie-Louise Elisabeth Labouret and Thomas-Alexandre Dumas Davy de la Pailleterie, a Revolutionary War general from Saint-Domingue, Alexandre Dumas (also known as Alexandre Dumas père) was among the most popular French playwrights and novelists of the nineteenth century. Dumas received early education in his native Villers-Cotterets from Abbé Grégoire, who ran a local school. By the 1830’s, Dumas was a successful dramatist and a leading figure in the Romantic movement, though he was not favored by contemporary critics. Over the course of the twentieth century, Dumas’ canonical status would be solidified, culminating with the transfer of his remains to the Pantheon in 2002.</p>
                <bibl>Daut, Marlene L. “Haiti and the Black Romantics: Enlightenment and Color Prejudice after the Haitian Revolution in Alexandre Dumas’s Georges (1843).” <title>Studies in Romanticism</title>, vol. 56, no. 1 (2017): 73–92.</bibl>
                <bibl>Desormeaux, Daniel. “L’amour Nègre Chez Alexandre Dumas.” In <title>Dumas Amoureux : Formes et Imaginaires de l’Éros Dumasien</title>, edited by Julie Anselmini and Claude Schopp, 373–87. Presses universitaires de Caen, 2021.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martone, Eric, ed. <title>Alexandre Dumas as a French Symbol Since 1870</title>. Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2021.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="CB">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Cyrille Bissette</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Born in Fort-Royal (now Fort-de-France, Martinique) on July 9, 1795, Cyrille Charles Auguste Bissette was the founder and editor-in-chief of the Revue des Colonies, the first French press outlet to advocate for immediate and total abolition. His parents, Charles Borromée Bissette and Elizabeth Mélanie Bellaine, were free people of color, and his mother was the illegitimate daughter of Joseph-Gaspard de Tascher de La Pagerie, making Bissette a nephew of Empress Joséphine de Beauharnais.</p>
                <bibl>Bongie, Chris. “1835, ou ‘Le troisième cycle’: The Creole Afterlives of Cyrille-Charles Auguste Bissette, Louis de Maynard de Queilhe, and Victor Schoelcher.” In <title>Islands and Exiles: The Creole Identities of Post/Colonial Literature</title>. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1998. 264-287, 323-340.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bongie, Chris. “A Street Named Bissette: Assimilating the Cent-cinquantenaire of the Abolition of Slavery in Martinique (1848–1998).” In <title>Friends and Enemies, </title>vol.3. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press. 2008. 185‑220.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. “Cyrille Bissette, Radical Black French Abolitionist.” French History 9.1 (1995): p. 48-66</bibl>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. <title>French Anti-Slavery: The Movement for the Abolition of Slavery in France, 1802-1848</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000. 29-37, 49-50, 71-73, 266-69.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mesnard, Eric. “Les Mouvements de Résistance dans les colonies franchisées : L'affaire Bissette (1823-1827).” In <title>The Abolitions of Slavery : From Leger Felicite Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>, edited by Marcel Dorigny. Paris: UNESCO, 2003. 293-97.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pâme, Stella. <title>Cyrille Bissette: un martyr de la liberté</title>. Fort-de-France, Martinique: Editions Désormeaux, 1999.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Né à Fort-Royal (Martinique) le 9 juillet 1795, Cyrille Charles Auguste Bissette est le fondateur et rédacteur en chef de la <title>Revue des Colonies</title>, premier organe de presse à plaider publiquement pour une abolition immédiate.</p>
                <bibl>Bongie, Chris. “1835, ou ‘Le troisième cycle’: The Creole Afterlives of Cyrille-Charles Auguste Bissette, Louis de Maynard de Queilhe, and Victor Schoelcher.” In <title>Islands and Exiles: The Creole Identities of Post/Colonial Literature</title>. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 1998. 264-287, 323-340.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bongie, Chris. “A Street Named Bissette: Assimilating the Cent-cinquantenaire of the Abolition of Slavery in Martinique (1848–1998).” In <title>Friends and Enemies, </title>vol.3. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press. 2008. 185‑220.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. “Cyrille Bissette, Radical Black French Abolitionist.” French History 9.1 (1995): p. 48-66</bibl>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. <title>French Anti-Slavery: The Movement for the Abolition of Slavery in France, 1802-1848</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000. 29-37, 49-50, 71-73, 266-69.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mesnard, Eric. “Les Mouvements de Résistance dans les colonies franchisées : L'affaire Bissette (1823-1827).” In <title>The Abolitions of Slavery : From Leger Felicite Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>, edited by Marcel Dorigny. Paris: UNESCO, 2003. 293-97.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pâme, Stella. <title>Cyrille Bissette: un martyr de la liberté</title>. Fort-de-France, Martinique: Editions Désormeaux, 1999.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="Stx">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Léger-Félicité Sonthonax</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>A lawyer in the <title>Parlement</title> of Paris (the regional appellate court) on the eve of the Revolution, Léger-Félicité Sonthonax frequented the Jacobin Club where he associated with Étienne Polverel and Jacques Pierre Brissot, founder of the <title>Société des Amis des Noirs</title>. He was sent with Polverel as part of the Civil Commission to Saint-Domingue to enforce the law of April 4, 1792 recognizing the political rights of free people of color. Faced with major anti-slavery insurgencies and the Spanish-British alliance against France, the two civil commissioners gradually granted freedom to all Africans and descendants of Africans who agreed to fight for the Republic. Sonthonax’s August 29, 1793 proclamation formalized the general emancipation in the Northern Province.</p>
                <bibl>Dorigny, Marcel, ed. <title>The Abolitions of Slavery: From Leger Felicite Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>. Paris: UNESCO, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title> (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Avocat au parlement de Paris à la veille de la Révolution, Léger-Félicité Sonthonax fréquente le club des Jacobins où il fait la connaissance d’Étienne Polverel et de Jacques Pierre Brissot, créateur de la <title>Société des Amis des Noirs</title>, en 1788. Nommé commissaire civil, il est envoyé avec Polverel à Saint-Domingue pour faire appliquer la loi du 4 avril 1792 reconnaissant les droits politiques des « libres de couleur ». Face aux importantes insurrections antiesclavagistes et à l’alliance hispano-britannique contre la France, les deux commissaires civils accordent de manière ponctuelle la liberté à tous les Africains et descendants d’Africains acceptant de combattre sous les drapeaux de la République. La proclamation de Sonthonax, le 29 août 1793, officialise l’émancipation générale dans la partie Nord de l’île.</p>
                <bibl>Dorigny, Marcel, éd. <title>Les Abolitions de l’esclavage: de L.F. Sonthonax à V. Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>. Paris: Presses universitaires de Vincennes, UNESCO, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title>.  (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="NB">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Napoléon Bonaparte</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>In 1802, Napoleon Bonaparte, then First Consul of the French Republican government, later Emperor, reestablished slavery in the colonies where it had been abolished or partially abolished in 1794 and reaffirmed it in the colonial territories where abolition had not taken effect, such as Martinique. His invasion of Saint-Domingue to reestablish slavery there was repulsed, resulting in the declaration of an independent Haiti. </p>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>En 1802, Napoléon Bonaparte, alors Premier Consul du gouvernement républicain français, plus tard empereur, rétablit l’esclavage dans les colonies où il avait été aboli ou partiellement aboli en 1794 et le ratifie sur les territoires coloniaux où l’abolition n’avait pas pris effet, comme par exemple la Martinique. Son invasion de Saint-Domingue pour y rétablir l’esclavage a été repoussée, aboutissant à la déclaration d’une Haïti indépendante. </p>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="Plv">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Étienne Polverel</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>A lawyer in the <title>Parlement </title>of Paris (the regional appellate court), Étienne Polverel became secretary of the Jacobin Club in 1790, where he was introduced to Léger-Félicité Sonthonax and Jacques Pierre Brissot, founder of the <title>Société des Amis des Noirs</title>. Appointed civil commissioner, he was sent with Sonthonax to Saint-Domingue to enforce the law of April 4, 1792 recognizing the political rights of free people of color. Faced with important anti-slavery insurrections and the Spanish-British alliance against France, the two civil commissioners gradually granted freedom to all Africans and Afro-descendants agreeing to fight for the Republic. In September 1793, Polverel extended to the western part of the island under his jurisdiction the general emancipation proclaimed in the Northern Province by Sonthonax on 29 August 1793.</p>
                <bibl>Dorigny, Marcel, ed. <title>The Abolitions of Slavery: From Leger Felicite Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>. Paris: UNESCO, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title> (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Issu de l’aristocratie provinciale, Étienne Polverel est avocat au parlement de Paris à partir de 1780. Secrétaire du club des Jacobins dès 1790, il s’y lie avec Léger-Félicité Sonthonax et Jacques Pierre Brissot, créateur de la <title>Société des Amis des Noirs</title>, en 1788. Nommé commissaire civil, il est envoyé avec Sonthonax à Saint-Domingue pour faire appliquer la loi du 4 avril 1792 reconnaissant les droits politiques des « libres de couleur ». Face aux importantes insurrections antiesclavagistes et à l’alliance hispano-britannique contre la France, les deux commissaires civils accordent de manière ponctuelle la liberté à tous les Africains et descendants d’Africains acceptant de combattre sous les drapeaux de la République. Responsable de la partie Ouest de l’île, Polverel y étend, en septembre 1793, l’émancipation générale proclamée par Sonthonax dans la province du Nord le 29 août 1793.</p>
                <bibl>Dorigny, Marcel, éd. <title>Les Abolitions de l’esclavage: de L.F. Sonthonax à V. Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>. Paris: Presses universitaires de Vincennes, UNESCO, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title>.  (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="LaF">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Gilbert du Motier, marquis de Lafayette</persName>
            <birth>1757</birth>
            <death>1834</death>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#greg">
                <p>Born into an aristocratic family in Auvergne in 1757, Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier spent his early years there before moving to Paris to study at the Collège du Plessis, which would later become Louis-le-Grand high school. Following his family's tradition, he embarked on a military career, eventually becoming a cavalry officer.</p>
                <bibl>Étienne Taillemitte, “La Fayette et l’abolition de l’esclavage,” <title>L'esclave et les plantations : de l'établissement de la servitude à son abolition. Hommage à Pierre Pluchon</title>. Presses universitaires de Rennes, 2009. http://books.openedition.org/pur/97682.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#greg">
                <p>Issu de la noblesse fortunée, Marie-Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier naît en 1757 en Auvergne, où il grandit avant de poursuivre ses études à Paris au collège du Plessis (futur lycée Louis le Grand). Suivant la tradition familiale il poursuit une carrière militaire et devient officier de cavalerie. Informé des troubles agitant les colonies anglaises d’Amérique du Nord, Lafayette rejoint les insurgés, faisant usage de sa colossale fortune personnelle pour soutenir l’effort de guerre. Son engagement fait de lui un héros des deux côtés de l’Atlantique. Il participe aux discussions menant au Traité de Paris en 1783, et se voit nommé maréchal de camp par Louis XVI. Connu pour ses convictions progressistes, il est un des rares représentants de la noblesse à prêter serment au Jeu de Paume aux États-Généraux de 1789. Il rédige dans les journées qui suivent le premier jet de la Déclaration des Droits de l’Homme et du Citoyen.</p>
                <bibl>Étienne Taillemitte, « La Fayette et l’abolition de l’esclavage », <title>L'esclave et les plantations : de l'établissement de la servitude à son abolition. Hommage à Pierre Pluchon</title>. Rennes : Presses universitaires de Rennes, 2009 (généré le 28 septembre 2023). <ref target="">http://books.openedition.org/pur/97682</ref>.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="Dfy">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Louis-­Pierre Dufay</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Louis-­Pierre Dufay (or Dufaÿ, Bissette’s spelling is not standard) was among the deputies sent to represent Saint-Domingue in the National Convention as a result of the elections of 1793 and subsequently supported the abolition of 1794. Prior to this political reversal, however, he had been a member of the Club de l’hôtel de Massiac, an association of Caribbean planters who opposed the the early abolitionist group <title>La Société des amis des Noirs </title>and opposed the application of the Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen to the colonies.</p>
                <bibl>Benzaken, Jean-­Charles. “Louis-­Pierre Dufay, député abo­­li­­tion­­niste et homme d’affaires avisé. Esquisse bio­­gra­­phique.” <title>Annales historiques de la Révolution française</title> 368 (2012): 61‑85.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Louis-­Pierre Dufay (ou Dufahy, l’orthographe employée par Bissette est peu répandue) est parmi les députés envoyés pour représenter Saint-Domingue à la Convention à l’issue des élections de 1793 et ​​soutient par la suite l’abolition de 1794. Avant ce revirement politique, cependant , il avait été membre du Club de l’hôtel de Massiac, une association de propriétaires terriens caribéens qui s'opposaient au premier groupe abolitionniste La Société des amis des Noirs et s'opposaient à l'application de la Déclaration des droits de l'homme et du citoyen aux colonies.</p>
                <bibl>Benzaken, Jean-­Charles. « Louis-­Pierre Dufahy, député abo­­li­­tion­­niste et homme d’affaires avisé. Esquisse bio­­gra­­phique », <title>Annales historiques de la Révolution française</title>. 1 juin 2012 n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 368. p. 61‑85.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="Equ">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Olaudah Equiano</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Olaudah Equiano was among the most prominent British abolitionists of the late eighteenth century. Born around 1745, he was sold as a child to the British captain Michael Pascal, who gave him the name Gustavas Vassa, which remained his legal name for the remainder of his life. Equiano served in the British Navy during the Seven Years’ War and in 1766, he purchased his freedom from the American merchant Robert King.</p>
                <bibl>Equiano, Olaudah. <title>The Interesting Narrative</title>, edited by Brycchan Carey. Oxford University Press 2018.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#masha">
                <p>Olaudah Equiano was among the most prominent British abolitionists of the late eighteenth century. Born around 1745, he was sold as a child to the British captain Michael Pascal, who gave him the name Gustavus Vassa, which remained his legal name for the remainder of his life. Equiano served in the British Navy during the Seven Years’ War and in 1766, he purchased his freedom from the American merchant Robert King.</p>
                <bibl>Equiano, Olaudah. <title>The Interesting Narrative</title>, edited by Brycchan Carey. Oxford University Press 2018.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="DES">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Pierre Dessalles</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#abel">
                <p>Pierre François Marie Dieudonné Dessalles, better known as Pierre Dessalles, was born in Castillonnès, in the department of Lot-et-Garonne and died at the age of 71 on March 5, 1857, in Brest. The son of Régis Dessalles and Manon d’Albis de Gissac, he married Anna Bence de Sainte-Catherine, a white Creole from Le Lamentin, in Fort-Royal, the administrative capital of the Martinique colony on October 6, 1808.</p>
                <bibl>Henri de Frémont, <title>Histoire et généalogie de la famille Dessalles ou Des Salles</title>, <ref target="">https://gw.geneanet.org/pierfit?lang=fr&amp;p=pierre&amp;n=dessalles&amp;oc=3</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Abel Alexis Louis, <title>Marchands et négociants de couleur à Saint-Pierre (1777-1830) : milieux socioprofessionnels, fortune et mode de vie</title>, Paris, L’Harmattan, 2015.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#abel">
                <p>Né à Castillonnès dans le département du Lot-et-Garonne, il décède le 5 mars 1857 à Brest à l’âge de 71 ans. Pierre François Marie Dieudonné Dessalles, plus connu en tant que Pierre Dessalles, était le fils de Régis Dessalles et de Manon d’Albis de Gissac. Marié le 6 octobre 1808 à Fort-Royal, capitale administrative de la colonie de la Martinique, à Anna Bence de Sainte-Catherine, blanche créole du Lamentin, Pierre Dessalles, bien que métropolitain, fut l’archétype du colon blanc par sa famille paternelle et maternelle, ainsi que par son alliance matrimoniale. Il fit une carrière dans la magistrature en tant que conseiller à la Cour d’appel de la Martinique (assesseur le 4 janvier 1809, titulaire le 4 janvier 1812). C’est à ce titre qu’il prit part à l’affaire Bissette (1823-1824) et fit condamner Cyrille Auguste Bissette aux galères à perpétuité et à être marqué au fer rouge des lettres GAL (Galérien). Puis, il fut conseiller à la Cour royale de la Martinique le 5 octobre 1828. Il fut aussi capitaine dans les milices de la colonie le 25 février 1829. Nommé ensuite procureur général par intérim à la Cour d’appel le 16 juin 1831, il fut démissionnaire le 31 juillet suivant, suspendu le 4 août 1832, et destitué le 19 septembre 1832. L’homme fut aussi propriétaire d’habitations, sucrerie et caféière à Sainte-Marie, commune du nord atlantique de la Martinique. Fin connaisseur de la société coloniale esclavagiste de la Martinique, il s’épancha sur cette dernière dans son ouvrage intitulé « La Vie d’un colon à la Martinique au XIX<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle » (1808-1856) dans lequel il revint sur plusieurs évènements marquants comme les révoltes d’esclaves (ou plus exactement d’esclavisés) en 1811 et 1831, l’affaire Bissette en 1823-1824, l’affaire de la Grande Anse en 1833 et les prémices de l’abolition de l’esclavage en Martinique.</p>
                <bibl>Henri de Frémont, <title>Histoire et généalogie de la famille Dessalles ou Des Salles</title>, <ref target="">https://gw.geneanet.org/pierfit?lang=fr&amp;p=pierre&amp;n=dessalles&amp;oc=3</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl>Abel Alexis Louis, <title>Marchands et négociants de couleur à Saint-Pierre (1777-1830) : milieux socioprofessionnels, fortune et mode de vie</title>, Paris, L’Harmattan, 2015.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
        <person xml:id="RL">
            <persName xml:lang="en"/>
            <persName xml:lang="fr">Pierre-François Honoré Richard de Lucy de Fossarieu</persName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Person" resp="#abel">
                <p>Born in Saint-Pierre on December 18, 1790 and died in the same town on February 1, 1839, at the age of 48, Pierre-François Honoré Richard de Lucy de Fossarieu belonged to an affluent settler family in colonial Martinique, with his father, Xavier Lucy de Fossarieu, holding the rank of infantry captain. On February 3, 1814, he married Claire Elisabeth Eyma, a fellow white Creole, whose family had ties to his through her mother Hélène de Lussy de Fossarieu. He served as a counselor at the Royal Court of Martinique in 1821 and President of the General Council in 1830, following his tenure as interim Attorney General from 1822 to 1824, in which capacity he oversaw the execution of the verdict of condemnation against Cyrille Bissette in January 1824.</p>
                <bibl>Françoise Thésée, “La Révolte des esclaves du Carbet à la Martinique (octobre-novembre 1822)”, <title>Revue Française d’Histoire d’Outre-Mer</title>, 80-301, 1993, 551-584 [n. 54, 568]. DOI: https//doi.org/10.3406/outre.1993.3148.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Person" resp="#abel">
                <p>Né à Saint-Pierre le 18 décembre 1790, il y décède le 1<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> février 1839 à l’âge de 48 ans. Ce blanc créole appartenait à une riche famille de colons de la Martinique. Son père Xavier Lucy de Fossarieu fut d’ailleurs capitaine d’infanterie. Richard de Lucy de Fossarieu épousa le 3 février 1814 Claire Elisabeth Eyma, blanche créole dont la famille était apparentée à son futur époux par sa mère Hélène de Lussy de Fossarieu. Il fut conseiller à la Cour royale de la Martinique en 1821, procureur général par intérim de 1822 à 1824 et président du Conseil général en 1830. C’est lui qui fit exécuter l’arrêt de condamnation contre Cyrille Bissette en janvier 1824.</p>
                <bibl>Françoise Thésée, « La Révolte des esclaves du Carbet à la Martinique (octobre-novembre 1822) », <title>Revue Française d’Histoire d’Outre-Mer</title>, tome 80, n° 301, 4e trimestre 1993, pp. 551-584 [note 54, p. 568]. DOI : <ref target="">https//doi.org/10.3406/outre.1993.3148</ref>.</bibl>
            </note>
        </person>
    </listPerson>
    <listPlace>
        <place xml:id="DOM">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Dominique</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Dominica, located directly between Guadeloupe and Martinique, was first settled by French settlers from these islands in the late seventeenth century, who soon brought in African slaves. Like Martinique and Guadeloupe, Dominica was taken by British forces during the Seven Years' War. Unlike those islands, however, it remained under British control. After a French re-invasion in 1775, the colony was formally returned to the British in 1783 and remained under British control until its independence in 1978.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>La Dominique, située directement entre la Guadeloupe et la Martinique, a d’abord été colonisée par des colons français de ces îles à la fin du XVIIe siècle, qui ont rapidement amené des esclaves africains. Comme la Martinique et la Guadeloupe, la Dominique a été prise par les forces britanniques pendant la guerre de Sept Ans. Contrairement à ces îles, cependant, elle est restée sous contrôle britannique. Après une ré-invasion française en 1775, la colonie est formellement rendue aux Britanniques en 1783 et resta sous contrôle britannique jusqu’à son indépendance en 1978. </p>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="Alg">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Alger</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>French forces first entered the city of Algiers in July, 1830, in the closing days of the reign of Charles X, with formal military annexation beginning in 1834. At the time of the <title>Revue</title>’s initial publication, Algiers was metonymic of all the conquests carried out during the “pacification” operations, constituting a territory too restricted to be perceived distinctly from the city. It was in 1847, when the conquest took a definitive turn with the surrender of Abd el-Kader, that the territory of colonial Algeria began to expand in a precipitous manner. Although it generally opposes the violence of the occupying forces, the <title>Revue </title>is never explicitly critical of the colonization of Algeria.</p>
                <bibl>Bouchène, Abderrahmane, Jean-Pierre Peyroulou, Ouanassa Siari Tengour, Sylvie Thénault, eds. <title>Histoire de l’Algérie à la période coloniale, 1830-1962. </title>Paris: La Découverte, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sessions, Jennifer E. <title>By Sword and Plow: France and the Conquest of Algeria</title>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Les forces françaises entrent pour la première fois dans la ville d’Alger en juillet 1830, dans les derniers jours du règne de Charles X, avec une annexion militaire formelle commençant en 1834. Au moment de la première livraison de la <title>Revue</title>, Alger est métonymique de l’ensemble des conquêtes effectuées au cours des opérations de « pacification », constituant un territoire trop restreint pour être perçu différemment de la ville. C’est en 1847, lorsque la conquête amorce un tournant définitif avec la reddition d’Abd el-Kader, que le territoire de l’Algérie coloniale commence à s’étendre de manière précipitée. Bien qu’elle soit généralement opposée à la violence des forces d’occupation, la <title>Revue </title>ne se montre jamais explicitement hostile à la colonisation de l’Algérie.</p>
                <bibl>Bouchène, Abderrahmane, Jean-Pierre Peyroulou, Ouanassa Siari Tengour, Sylvie Thénault, eds. <title>Histoire de l’Algérie à la période coloniale, 1830-1962. </title>Paris: La Découverte, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sessions, Jennifer E. <title>By Sword and Plow: France and the Conquest of Algeria</title>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2014.</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ANG">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Angleterre </placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>As both France’s primary military and colonial rival and a model for the French abolitionist movement, England is a particularly interesting topic of coverage within the <title>Revue.</title></p>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. “Slavery and the Venality of the July Monarchy Press.” <title>French Historical Studies</title> 17.4 (1992): 957–78.</bibl>
                <bibl>Walvin, James. "British Abolitionism, 1787-1838." In <title>The Abolitions of Slavery: From the LF Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>,edited by Marcel Dorigny (New York: Bergham Books, 2003), 71-78</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>À la fois puissance militaire et coloniale rivale de la France et modèle du mouvement abolitionniste français, l’Angleterre bénéficie, au sein de la <title>Revue, </title>d’une couverture médiatique particulièrement intéressante.</p>
                <bibl>Jennings, Lawrence C. “Slavery and the Venality of the July Monarchy Press.” <title>French Historical Studies</title> 17.4 (1992): 957–78.</bibl>
                <bibl>Walvin, James. "British Abolitionism, 1787-1838." In <title>The Abolitions of Slavery: From the LF Sonthonax to Victor Schoelcher, 1793, 1794, 1848</title>,edited by Marcel Dorigny (New York: Bergham Books, 2003), 71-78</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="BrB">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Bourbon</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Located in the Indian Ocean to the east of Madagascar, the island of Bourbon has been under French control since the seventeenth century. Renamed Réunion during the Revolution, then Bonaparte Island under the Empire, it was occupied by the British between 1810 and 1814, before definitively returning to France in the Treaty of Paris. First used as a stopover for the ships of the French East India Company, the island adopted a slave plantation economy in the first half of the eighteenth century. According to the 1788 census, approximately 80% of the island’s population, originating in Africa, Madagascar or India, was enslaved. The abolition decreed by the Convention on February 4, 1794 was never actually applied and acts of resistance, notably <title>marronage</title>, were common.</p>
                <bibl>Ève, Prosper. <title>Naître et mourir à l’île Bourbon à l’époque de l’esclavage</title>. Paris &amp; Saint-Denis: L’Harmattan, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Little, Roger et Pratima Prasad (eds.). <title>Esclaves marrons à Bourbon Une anthologie littéraire (1831-1848)</title>. 2005. vol.64.</bibl>
                <bibl>Prasad, Pratima. « Colour and Conflict in Nineteenth-Century Île Bourbon: the Case of the Affaire Houat », Dix-Neuf. 2 janvier 2020, vol.24 no 1. p. 1‑16.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Située dans l’océan Indien à l’est de Madagascar, l’île de Bourbon est sous contrôle français depuis le 17e siècle. Devenue Réunion à la Révolution, puis île Bonaparte sous l’Empire, elle est occupée par les Britanniques entre 1810 et 1814, avant d’être définitivement rendue à la France dans le cadre du traité de Paris. D’abord employée comme escale pour les navires de la Compagnie française des Indes orientales, l’île intègre, dans la première moitié du 18e siècle, le modèle de la société de plantation esclavagiste. D’après le recensement de 1788, environ 80% de la population de l’île, d’origine africaine, malgache, ou indienne, est esclavisée. L’esclavagisme bourbonnais repose, par ailleurs, sur une politique de division éthnique d’africains, de malgaches et d’indiens dans le but d’éviter la constitution d’un groupe majoritaire menaçant pour l’ordre colonial. L’abolition décrétée par la Convention le 4 février 1794, n’y est jamais appliquée et les actes de résistance, notamment le marronnage, sont répandus.</p>
                <bibl>Ève, Prosper. <title>Naître et mourir à l’île Bourbon à l’époque de l’esclavage</title>. Paris &amp; Saint-Denis: L’Harmattan, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Little, Roger et Pratima Prasad (eds.). <title>Esclaves marrons à Bourbon Une anthologie littéraire (1831-1848)</title>. 2005. vol.64.</bibl>
                <bibl>Prasad, Pratima. « Colour and Conflict in Nineteenth-Century Île Bourbon: the Case of the Affaire Houat », Dix-Neuf. 2 janvier 2020, vol.24 no 1. p. 1‑16.</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="Cay">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Cayenne </placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>The island of Cayenne, in the estuary of the river of the same name, is also the location of the city of Cayenne, the capital of French Guiana. According to the 1788 census, Cayenne’s enslaved population represented just over 80% of the total population. During the Revolution, Cayenne received multiple convoys of exiles from metropolitan France, beginning its eventual transformation into a penal colony in the nineteenth century. The 1794 abolition decree was never meaningfully enforced there. Victor Hugues, the commissioner in charge of enforcing the decree in Guadeloupe, was named governor of Guiana in 1799, replacing slavery with a system of conscripted labor until the official restoration of slavery in 1802 by the decree of First Consul Napoleon Bonaparte. This regression to pre-Revolutionary conditions led to high frequencies of marronage. Conquered by Portuguese forces in 1809, the colony was returned to France in 1817, following the Treaty of Paris. From its inaugural issue, the <title>Revue des Colonie</title> features regular reports from a correspondent in Cayenne, including detailed electoral data.</p>
                <bibl>Mam Lam Fouck, Serge. <title>La Guyane française au temps de l'esclavage, de l'or et de la francisation (1802-1946)</title>. Matoury, French Guiana: Ibis Rouge Editions, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>La France a-t-elle aboli l'esclavage ? Guadeloupe, Martinique, Guyane, 1830-1935</title>. Paris: Perrin, 2009.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Situé sur l’île de Cayenne, dans l’estuaire de la rivière du même nom, Cayenne est le chef-lieu de la Guyane française. Issue du premier empire colonial français, voisine du Brésil et du Suriname, cette colonie fondée sur l’économie de plantation devient un lieu de déportation lors de la Révolution française, accueillant plusieurs convois de proscrits. D’après le recensement de 1788, la population esclavisée y représente un peu plus de 80% de la population. L’abolition de l’esclavage, en application du décret de la Convention, y est proclamée le 14 juin 1794. En 1802, Victor Hugues, le commissaire chargé de faire appliquer le décret d’abolition de l’esclavage en Guadeloupe, y impose le rétablissement de l’esclavage promulgué en 1802 par Napoléon Bonaparte, Premier Consul, et instaure un régime de conscription locale. Cette régression aux dispositions antérieures à la Révolution entraîne d’importants mouvements de marronnage. Conquise par les forces portugaises en 1809, la colonie est restituée à la France en 1817, à l’issue du traité de Paris. La <title>Revue des Colonies </title>dispose d’un correspondant à Cayenne qui rend compte des nouvelles, notamment électorales, de Guyane dès la première livraison.</p>
                <bibl>Mam Lam Fouck, Serge. <title>La Guyane française au temps de l'esclavage, de l'or et de la francisation (1802-1946)</title>. Matoury, French Guiana: Ibis Rouge Editions, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>La France a-t-elle aboli l'esclavage ? Guadeloupe, Martinique, Guyane, 1830-1935</title>. Paris: Perrin, 2009.</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="Esk">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Essaka</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>The place of birth of Oladuah Equiano, according to his autobiography <title>The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, Or Gustavus Vassa, The African</title>. This work, which is the source for the chapter on Equiano in Abbé Grégoire’s <title>De la littérature des nègres</title> reprinted in the <title>Revue</title>, contains the only known reference to “Essaka” with this spelling. The actual place of Equiano’s birth has been the subject of some debate, with some claiming that Essaka refers to Issieke, in Igboland, present day Nigeria. Other scholars have pointed out that Equiano’s baptismal records (whose information would have been provided by the family of his master), and other documents from his naval career, list his place of birth as South Carolina.</p>
                <bibl>Lovejoy, Paul E. "Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa, What's in a Name?" <title>Atlantic Studies</title> 9.2 (2012), 165-84.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>The place of birth of Oladuah Equiano, according to his autobiography <title>The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano, Or Gustavus Vassa, The African</title>. This work, which is the source for the chapter on Equiano in Abbé Grégoire’s <title>De la littérature des nègres</title> reprinted in the <title>Revue</title>, contains the only known reference to “Essaka” with this spelling. The actual place of Equiano’s birth has been the subject of some debate, with some claiming that Essaka refers to Issieke, in Igboland, present day Nigeria. Other scholars have pointed out that Equiano’s baptismal records (whose information would have been provided by the family of his master), and other documents from his naval career, list his place of birth as South Carolina.</p>
                <bibl>Lovejoy, Paul E. "Olaudah Equiano or Gustavus Vassa, What's in a Name?" <title>Atlantic Studies</title> 9.2 (2012), 165-84.</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="HT">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Haiti</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>The former colony of Saint-Domingue, located on the western part of the island of Hispaniola, was by far the most profitable territory of the first French colonial empire. In 1789, 90% of its population of almost half a million consisted of enslaved people, who produced three quarters of the world's sugar.</p>
                <bibl>Brickhouse, Anna. <title>Transamerican Literary Relations and Nineteenth-Century Public Sphere</title>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004</bibl>
                <bibl>Daut, Marlene. <title>Tropics of Haiti: Race and the Literary History of the Haitian Revolution in the Atlantic World, 1789-1865</title>. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2015</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title> (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pierrot, Grégory. <title>The Black Avenger in Atlantic Culture</title>. Athens: The University of Georgia Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stieber, Chelsea. <title>Haiti’s Paper War: Post-Independence Writing, Civil War, and the Making of the Republic, 1804-1954</title>. New York: New York University Press, 2020.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>L’ancienne colonie de Saint-Domingue, située sur la partie occidentale de l’île d’Hispaniola, était de loin le territoire le plus profitable du premier empire colonial français. En 1789, 90% de sa population de près d’un demi-million est esclavisée et produit trois quarts du sucre mondial.</p>
                <bibl>Brickhouse, Anna. <title>Transamerican Literary Relations and Nineteenth-Century Public Sphere</title>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004</bibl>
                <bibl>Daut, Marlene. <title>Tropics of Haiti: Race and the Literary History of the Haitian Revolution in the Atlantic World, 1789-1865</title>. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2015</bibl>
                <bibl>Dubois, Laurent. <title>Avengers of the New World: The Story of the Haitian Revolution</title>.  (Cambridge, Mass: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 2004).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pierrot, Grégory. <title>The Black Avenger in Atlantic Culture</title>. Athens: The University of Georgia Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stieber, Chelsea. <title>Haiti’s Paper War: Post-Independence Writing, Civil War, and the Making of the Republic, 1804-1954</title>. New York: New York University Press, 2020.</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="MQ">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Martinique</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Principally under French control since the mid seventeenth century, Martinique, like the neighboring archipelago of Guadeloupe, was part of the first French colonial empire. A slave plantation economy, mainly devoted to sugar monoculture, the island came under British control between 1759 and 1763, and again, in 1794, with the support of planters seeking to avoid the abolition decreed by the National Convention. According to the 1789 census, the enslaved population there represented approximately 84% of the total population, with 11% white and 5% free people of color.</p>
                <bibl>Kováts Beaudoux, Édith,<title> Les Blancs créoles de la Martinique : une minorité dominante</title>, préface de Michel Giraud, Paris, France, L’Harmattan, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Larcher, Silyane. <title>L’autre citoyen: L’idéal républicain et les Antilles après l’esclavage</title>. Paris: Armand Colin, 2014. 109-125.</bibl>
                <bibl>Régent, Frédéric. « Préjugé de couleur, esclavage et citoyennetés dans les colonies françaises (1789-1848) », <title>La Révolution française</title>. 17 novembre 2015 n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 9. En ligne : <ref target="">http://journals.openedition.org/lrf/1403</ref> [visited 13 November 2021].</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Principalement sous contrôle français depuis le milieu du 17e siècle, la Martinique, comme l’archipel guadeloupéen voisin, fait partie du premier empire colonial français. Il s’agit d’une société coloniale fondée sur une économie de plantation esclavagiste, principalement consacrée à la monoculture sucrière. L’île passe sous contrôle Britannique entre 1759 et 1763, et de nouveau, en 1794, avec l’appui des planteurs cherchant à se soustraire à l’abolition décrétée par la Convention. Lors du recensement de 1789, la population esclavisée y représente environ 84% du total, pour 11% de blancs et 5% de « libres de couleur ».</p>
                <bibl>Kováts Beaudoux, Édith,<title> Les Blancs créoles de la Martinique : une minorité dominante</title>, préface de Michel Giraud, Paris, France, L’Harmattan, 2003.</bibl>
                <bibl>Larcher, Silyane. <title>L’autre citoyen: L’idéal républicain et les Antilles après l’esclavage</title>. Paris: Armand Colin, 2014. 109-125.</bibl>
                <bibl>Régent, Frédéric. « Préjugé de couleur, esclavage et citoyennetés dans les colonies françaises (1789-1848) », <title>La Révolution française</title>. 17 novembre 2015 n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 9. En ligne : <ref target="">http://journals.openedition.org/lrf/1403</ref> [consulté le 13 novembre 2021].</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="GP">
            <placeName xml:lang="en"/>
            <placeName xml:lang="fr">Guadeloupe</placeName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Like Martinique, the Guadeloupe archipelago was part of the first French colonial empire of the seventeenth century. As a slave economy primarily devoted to sugar cultivation, the island’s enslaved population represented approximately 85% of the total, per the 1789 census, with 13% white and 3% “free people of color.” The archipelago came under British control between 1759 and 1763, and was briefly occupied again in 1794, following the National Convention’s abolition decree. This occupation was, however, expelled by military forces including several thousand newly emancipated men, led by Victor Hugues, the civil commissioner sent by the Convention to enforce the abolition decree. The implementation of this abolition was, however, largely symbolic, with chattel slavery replaced, in many instances, by forced labor. In 1802, a large insurrectionary army commanded by Louis Delgrès, a free man of color, opposed the French General Richepanse, who had been sent to restore slavery on the orders of Napoleon Bonaparte, then First Consul. The brutally repressed insurrection would end with the suicide of Delgrès and his company.</p>
                <bibl>Dorigny, Marcel, and Bernard Gainot, eds. <title>Atlas des esclavages. Traités, sociétés coloniales, abolitions, de l’Antiquité à nos jours</title>. Paris: Éditions Autrement, 2006</bibl>
                <bibl>Régent, Frédéric. « Préjugé de couleur, esclavage et citoyennetés dans les colonies françaises (1789-1848) », <title>La Révolution française</title>. 17 novembre 2015 n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 9. En ligne : <ref target="">http://journals.openedition.org/lrf/1403</ref> [visited 13 November 2021].</bibl>
                <bibl>Fallope, Josette. <title>Esclaves et citoyens. Les Noirs à la Guadeloupe au XIXe siècle dans les processus de résistance et d’intégration</title> (1802-1910), Basse-Terre, Bibliothèque d’Histoire antillaise, 1992</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Place" resp="#masha">
                <p>Comme son île voisine de la Martinique, l'archipel guadeloupéen fait partie du premier empire colonial français. Il s’agit d’une société coloniale fondée sur une économie de plantation esclavagiste, principalement consacrée à la monoculture sucrière. Lors du recensement de 1789, la population esclavisée y représente environ 85% du total, pour 13% de blancs et 3% de « libres de couleur ».</p>
                <bibl>Marcel Dorigny et Bernard Gainot. <title>Atlas des esclavages. Traités, sociétés coloniales, abolitions, de l’Antiquité à nos jours</title>. Paris : Éditions Autrement, 2006</bibl>
                <bibl>Régent, Frédéric. « Préjugé de couleur, esclavage et citoyennetés dans les colonies françaises (1789-1848) », <title>La Révolution française</title>. 17 novembre 2015 n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 9. En ligne : <ref target="">http://journals.openedition.org/lrf/1403</ref> [consulté le 13 novembre 2021].</bibl>
                <bibl>Fallope, Josette. <title>Esclaves et citoyens. Les Noirs à la Guadeloupe au XIXe siècle dans les processus de résistance et d’intégration</title> (1802-1910), Basse-Terre, Bibliothèque d’Histoire antillaise, 1992</bibl>
            </note>
        </place>
    </listPlace>
    <listOrg>
        <org xml:id="AN">
            <orgName xml:lang="en"/>
            <orgName xml:lang="fr">Assemblée Nationale</orgName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>The National Assembly was formed on June 17, 1789, one month after the meeting of the Estates General, by the deputies of the Third Estate. This date commonly marks the beginning of the French Revolution. </p>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>Il s’agit de l’Assemblée nationale auto-proclamée, le 17 juin 1789, soit un mois après la réunion des états généraux, par les députés du tiers état. Cette date est depuis retenue comme marquant le début de la Révolution française. </p>
            </note>
        </org>
        <org xml:id="CNat">
            <orgName xml:lang="en"/>
            <orgName xml:lang="fr">Convention Nationale</orgName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>An assembly of the French Revolution, it succeeded the Legislative Assembly in 1792, established the First Republic, and governed France until October 26, 1795.</p>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>L’abolition de l’esclavage: cinq siècles de combats (xvie - xxe siècle)</title>. Paris : Fayard, 2006.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>Assemblée constituante pendant la Révolution française, elle succède à l’Assemblée législative en 1792, fonde la Ière République et gouverne la France jusqu’au 26 octobre 1795.</p>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>L’abolition de l’esclavage: cinq siècles de combats (xvie - xxe siècle)</title>. Paris : Fayard, 2006.</bibl>
            </note>
        </org>
        <org xml:id="SHC">
            <orgName xml:lang="en"/>
            <orgName xml:lang="fr">Société d’Hommes de Couleur</orgName>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>The ephemeral presence of this “society” on the title page of the <title>Revue </title>(until January 1835), combined with the absence of any other documentary trace, suggests that it was more an editorial construction than a formal organization.</p>
                <bibl>Braun, Juliane. <title>Creole drama: Theatre and Society in Antebellum New Orleans</title>. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 2019. 141‑143.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pâme, Stella. <title>Cyrille Bisette</title>. 1. éd. Fort-de-France, Martinique: Editions Désormeaux. 1997. 123-124.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>Abolitionnistes de l'esclavage et réformateurs des colonies, 1820-1851: analyses et documents</title>. Paris: Karthala, 2000.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Organization" resp="#masha">
                <p>La présence éphémère de cette « société » sur la page de titre de la <title>Revue </title>(jusqu’en janvier 1835), conjuguée à l’absence de toute autre trace documentaire, suggère qu’il s’agirait d’une construction éditoriale plutôt que d’un véritable organisme associatif.</p>
                <bibl>Braun, Juliane. « Transatlantic Vistas: Changing Alliances at Home and Abroad » <title>Creole Drama</title>. University of Virginia Press. 2019, p. 141‑143.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pâme, Stella. <title>Cyrille Bisette</title>. 1. éd. Fort-de-France, Martinique: Editions Désormeaux. 1997. 123-124.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schmidt, Nelly. <title>Abolitionnistes de l'esclavage et réformateurs des colonies, 1820-1851: analyses et documents</title>. Paris: Karthala, 2000.</bibl>
            </note>
        </org>
    </listOrg>
    <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="RC" type="periodical">
            <title xml:lang="en"/>
            <title xml:lang="fr">Revue Coloniale</title>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Publication" resp="#masha">
                <p>The <title>Revue Coloniale</title>, was an ephemeral monthly periodical, printed in Paris during the year 1838. Its founder Édouard Bouvet and editor Rosemond Beauvallon conceived of it on the model of many similar, contemporaneous publications reporting on political and economic questions of interest to white colonists while also attending to arts and literature, as attested by the journal’s complete title: <title>Revue Coloniale. intérêts des colons : marine, commerce, littérature, beaux-arts, théâtres, modes</title>. In the December 1838 issue of the <title>Revue des Colonies</title>, Cyrille Bissette acknowledges the <title>Revue Coloniale</title> as both an ideological opponent and a competitor in the print market.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Publication" resp="#masha">
                <p>Fondée par Édouard Bouvet et dirigée par Rosemond Beauvallon, la <title>Revue Coloniale</title>, sous-titrée <title>intérêts des colons : marine, commerce, littérature, beaux-arts, théâtres, modes</title>, souscrit au modèle des revues destinées aux propriétaires coloniaux, rendant compte de l'actualité politique et économique des colonies tout en ménageant une place aux contenus littéraires, culturels et mondains. Dans le numéro de décembre 1838 de la <title>Revue des Colonies</title>, Cyrille Bissette reconnaît en la <title>Revue Coloniale</title> tant un adversaire idéologique qu'un concurrent dans le paysage médiatique.</p>
            </note>
        </bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="MU" type="periodical">
            <title xml:lang="en"/>
            <title xml:lang="fr">Le Moniteur universel</title>
            <note xml:lang="en" type="Publication" resp="#laure">
                <p><title>Le Moniteur universel</title>, often simply referred to as the “Le Moniteur” is one of the most frequently referenced nineteenth-century French newspapers. An important cultural signifier, it was referenced frequently in other publications, in fiction, and likely in contemporary discussions. Its title, derived from the verb <emph>monere</emph>, meaning to warn or advise, gestures at Enlightenment and Revolutionary ideals of intelligent counsel.</p>
                <bibl>Laurence Guellec, « Les journaux officiels », <title>La Civilisation du journal</title> (dir. Dominique Kalifa, Philippe Régnier, Marie-Ève Thérenty, Alain Vaillant), Paris, Nouveau Monde, 2011. <ref target="">https://www.retronews.fr/titre-de-presse/gazette-nationale-ou-le-moniteur-universel</ref>.</bibl>
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="fr" type="Publication" resp="#laure">
                <p><title>Le Moniteur universel</title>, ou « Le Moniteur », est l’un des journaux les plus cités, sous cette forme abrégée et familière, au cours du XIX<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle : on le retrouve, véritable élément de civilisation, dans la presse, dans les fictions, probablement dans les discussions d’alors. Ce titre, qui renvoie au langage des Lumières et de la Révolution, dérive étymologiquement du verbe <emph>monere</emph>, signifiant avertir ou conseiller. Il n’est d’abord que le sous-titre de la <title>Gazette nationale</title>, créée en 1789 par Charles-Joseph Panckouke, éditeur entre autres de l’<title>Encyclopédie</title> de Diderot et d’Alembert ; ce n’est qu’en 1811 que le sous-titre, <title>Le Moniteur universel</title>, devient officiellement titre.</p>
                <bibl>Laurence Guellec, « Les journaux officiels », <title>La Civilisation du journal</title> (dir. Dominique Kalifa, Philippe Régnier, Marie-Ève Thérenty, Alain Vaillant), Paris, Nouveau Monde, 2011. <ref target="">https://www.retronews.fr/titre-de-presse/gazette-nationale-ou-le-moniteur-universel</ref>.</bibl>
            </note>
        </bibl>
    </listBibl>
</div>